<!-- jEdit buffer-local properties: -->
<!-- :indentSize=1:noTabs=true: -->

<chapter id="basics"><title>jEdit Basics</title>
 <sect1 id="buffers"><title>Buffers</title>
  <para>
   Several files can be opened and edited at once.
   Each open file is referred to as a <firstterm>buffer</firstterm>.
   The combo box above the text area selects the buffer to edit.
   Different emblems are displayed next to buffer names in the list,
   depending the buffer's state;
   a red disk is shown for buffers with unsaved changes,
   a lock is shown for read-only buffers,
   and a spark is shown for new buffers which don't yet exist on disk.
  </para>
  <para>
   In addition to the buffer combo box, various commands can also be
   used to select the buffer to edit.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Go to Previous Buffer</guimenuitem>
   (keyboard shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>Page Up</keycap>
   </keycombo>) switches to the previous buffer in the list.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Go to Next Buffer</guimenuitem>
   (keyboard shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>Page Down</keycap>
   </keycombo>) switches to the next buffer in the list.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Go to Recent Buffer</guimenuitem>
   (keyboard shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>`</keycap></keycombo>)
   switches to the buffer that was being edited prior to the current one.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="views"><title>Views</title>
  <para>
   Each editor window is known as a <firstterm>view</firstterm>.
   It is possible to have multiple views open at once, and each view can
   be split into multiple panes.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>New View</guimenuitem> creates a new view.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Close View</guimenuitem> closes the
   current view. If only one view is open, closing it will exit jEdit,
   unless background mode is on; see <xref linkend="starting" /> for information
   about starting jEdit in background mode.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Splitting</guisubmenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Split
   Horizontally</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>2</keycap></keycombo>)
   splits the view into two text areas, above each other.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Splitting</guisubmenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Split
   Vertically</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>3</keycap></keycombo>)
   splits the view into two text areas, next to each other.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Splitting</guisubmenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Unsplit</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>1</keycap></keycombo>)
   removes all but the current text area from the view.
  </para>
  <para>
   When a view is split, editing commands operate on the text area that
   has keyboard focus. To give a text area keyboard focus, click in it
   with the mouse, or use the following commands.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Splitting</guisubmenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Go to
   Previous Text Area</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo>)
   shifts keyboard focus to the previous text area.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Splitting</guisubmenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Go to
   Next Text Area</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo>)
   shifts keyboard focus to the next text area.
  </para>
  <para>
   Clicking the text area with the right mouse button displays a popup menu.
   Both this menu and the tool bar at the top of the view offer quick
   mouse-based access to frequently-used commands.
   The contents of the tool bar and right-click menu can be
   changed in the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global
   Options</guimenuitem> dialog box.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="docking"><title>Window Docking</title>
   <para>
    The file system browser, HyperSearch results window, and many plugin
    windows can optionally be docked into the view. This can be
    configured in the <guibutton>Docking</guibutton> pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box; see <xref linkend="global-opts" />. Note that changes made in
    this option pane will not take effect
    immediately; you must restart jEdit or open a new view first.
   </para>
   <para>
    When windows are docked into the view,
    the commands in the <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Docking</guisubmenu>
    menu (shortcuts: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
    <keycap>1</keycap>, <keycap>2</keycap>, <keycap>3</keycap>, <keycap>4</keycap>)
    can be used
    to show or hide the top, bottom, left and right docking areas,
    respectively. Double-clicking on the borders of docking areas has
    the same effect.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>The Status Bar</title>
   <para>
    A <firstterm>status bar</firstterm> at the bottom of the view displays the
    following information, from left to right:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>The line number containing the caret</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The column position of the caret, with the leftmost column
    being 1.</para>
    <para>
     If the line contains tabs, the <firstterm>file</firstterm> position (where a hard
     tab is counted as one column) is shown first, followed by the
     <firstterm>screen</firstterm> position (where each tab counts for the number of
     columns until the next tab stop).
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Prompts displayed by commands such as those dealing with
    registers and markers (see <xref linkend="text-transfer" /> and <xref
    linkend="markers" />)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The current buffer's edit mode. Clicking this
    displays the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Buffer
    Options</guimenuitem> dialog box. See <xref
    linkend="modes" /> and <xref linkend="buffer-opts" />.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The current buffer's character encoding.  Clicking this
    displays the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Buffer
    Options</guimenuitem> dialog box. See <xref
    linkend="encodings" /> and <xref linkend="buffer-opts" />.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>If multiple selection is enabled, the text
    <guilabel>multi</guilabel> is shown in black, otherwise it will be grayed out.
    Clicking her or pressing <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap>
    <keycap>\</keycap></keycombo> turns multiple selection on and off. See <xref
    linkend="multi-select" />.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>If overwrite mode is enabled, the text <guilabel>over</guilabel> is
    shown in black, otherwise it will be grayed out. Clicking here or pressing
    <keycap>Insert</keycap> turns overwrite mode on and off. See <xref
    linkend="entering-text" />.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>If portions of the buffer are invisible due to folding,
    the text <guilabel>fold</guilabel> is
    shown in black, otherwise it will be grayed out. See <xref
    linkend="folding" />.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>If input/output operations are in progress, a small disk icon
    and progress bars for each running operation are displayed. Clicking
    here will display the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>I/O
    Progress Monitor</guimenuitem> dialog box. See <xref
    linkend="threaded-io" />.</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="textarea"><title>The Text Area</title>
  <para>
   Text editing takes place in the text area. It behaves in a similar
   manner to many Windows and MacOS editors; the few
   unique features will be described in this section.
  </para>
  <para>
   The text area will automatically scroll up or down if the caret is moved
   closer than three lines to the first or last visible line. This
   feature is called <firstterm>electric scrolling</firstterm> and can be disabled
   in the <guibutton>Text Area</guibutton> pane of the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box; see <xref linkend="global-opts" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   To aid in locating the caret, the current line is drawn with a
   different background color. To make it clear which lines end with
   white space, end of line markers are drawn at the end of each line.
   Both these features can be disabled in the <guibutton>Text Area</guibutton>
   pane of the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global
   Options</guimenuitem> dialog box.
  </para>
  <para>
   The strip on the left of the text area is called a <firstterm>gutter</firstterm>.
   The gutter displays marker and register locations; it will also display
   line numbers if the 
   <guimenu>View</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Line Numbers</guimenuitem> (shortcut:
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>T</keycap></keycombo>) command is invoked.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="repeat"><title>Command Repetition</title>
  <para>
   To repeat a command any number of times, invoke
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Repeat Next Command</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut:
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>) and enter the
   desired repeat count, followed by the command to repeat (either a keystroke
   or menu item selection). For example,
   <quote><keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>
   <keycap>1</keycap> <keycap>4</keycap>
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo></quote> will delete
   14 lines, and <quote><keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>
   <keycap>8</keycap>
   <keycap>#</keycap></quote>
   will insert <quote>########</quote> in the buffer.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you specify a repeat count greater than 20, a confirmation dialog box will
   be displayed, asking if you really want to perform the action. This prevents
   you from hanging jEdit by executing a command too many times.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
