<!-- jEdit buffer-local properties: -->
<!-- :tabSize=1:indentSize=1:noTabs=true:wrap=soft:maxLineLen=80: -->
<!-- :xml.root=users-guide.xml: -->

<chapter id="files"><title>Working With Files</title>
 <sect1 id="creating"><title>Creating New Files</title>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem> (shortcut:
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>) opens a new,
   empty, buffer.
   Another way to create a new file is to specify a non-existent file
   name when starting jEdit on the command line.
   A new file will be created on disk when the buffer is saved
   for the first time.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="opening"><title>Opening Files</title>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> (shortcut:
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo>) displays
   a file system browser dialog box and loads the specified file into a new
   buffer.
  </para>
  <para>
   Multiple files can be opened at once by holding down
   <keycap>Control</keycap> while clicking on them in the file system browser.
   The file system browser supports auto-completion;
   typing the first few characters of a listed file name will select the
   file.
  </para>
  <para>
   More advanced features of the file system browser are described in
   <xref linkend="vfs-browser"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Insert</guimenuitem> displays
   a file system browser dialog box and inserts the contents of
   the specified file at the caret position.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Recent Files</guimenuitem> menu
   lists recently viewed files. When a recent file is opened, the caret
   is automatically moved to its previous location in that file.
   The number of recent files to remember can be changed and caret
   position saving can be disabled in the <guibutton>General</guibutton> pane of
   the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box; see <xref linkend="global-opts" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Current Directory</guimenuitem>
   menu lists all files and directories in the current buffer's directory.
   Selecting a file opens it in a buffer for editing; selecting a directory
   opens it in the file system browser (see <xref linkend="vfs-browser" />).
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Files that you do not have write access to are opened in read-only
    mode, where editing is not permitted.
   </para>
  </note>
  <tip>
   <para>
    jEdit supports transparent editing of GZipped files; if a file begins with
    the GZip <quote>magic number</quote>, it is automatically decompressed
    before loading and compressed when saving. To compress an existing file,
    you need to change a setting in the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Buffer Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box; see <xref linkend="buffer-opts"/> for details.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="saving"><title>Saving Files</title>
  <para>
   Changed made in a buffer do not affect the file on disk until the
   buffer is <firstterm>saved</firstterm>.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem> (shortcut:
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>S</keycap></keycombo>)
   saves the current buffer to disk.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Save As</guimenuitem> renames
   the buffer and saves it in a new location. Note that
   using this command to save over another open buffer will close the other
   buffer, to stop two buffers from being able to share the same path name.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Save a Copy As</guimenuitem> saves
   the buffer to different location but does not rename it., but doesn't rename the
   buffer, and doesn't clear the <quote>modified</quote> flag. Note that
   using this command to save over another open buffer will automatically reload
   the other buffer.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Save All</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>S</keycap></keycombo>) saves all
   open buffers to disk, asking for confirmation first.
  </para>
  <sidebar><title>Two-stage save</title>
   <para>
    To prevent data loss in the unlikely case that jEdit should crash in the
    middle of saving a file, files are first saved to a temporary file named
    <filename>#<replaceable>filename</replaceable>#save#</filename>. If this
    operation is successful, the original file is replaced with the temporary
    file.
   </para>
   <para>
    However, in some situations, this behavior is undesirable. For example,
    on Unix saving files this way will result in the owner and group of the
    file being reset. If this bothers you, you can disable this so-called
    <quote>two-stage save</quote> in the <guibutton>Loading and Saving</guibutton>
    pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box.
   </para>
  </sidebar>
  <sect2><title>Autosave and Crash Recovery</title>
   <para>
    The autosave feature protects your work from computer crashes and
    such. Every 30 seconds, all buffers with unsaved changes are
    written out to their respective file names, enclosed in hash
    (<quote>#</quote>) characters. For example, <filename>program.c</filename>
    will be autosaved to <filename>#program.c#</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Saving a buffer using
    one of the commands in the previous section automatically deletes the
    autosave file, so they will only ever be visible in the unlikely
    event of a jEdit (or operating system) crash.
   </para>
   <para>
    If an autosave file is
    found while a buffer is being loaded, jEdit will offer to recover the
    autosaved data.
   </para>
   <para>
    The autosave interval can be changed
    in the <guibutton>Loading and Saving</guibutton> pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box; see <xref linkend="global-opts" />.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>Backups</title>
   <para>
    The backup feature can be used to roll back to the previous version
    of a file after changes were made. When a buffer is saved
    for the first time after being opened, its original contents are
    <quote>backed up</quote> under a different file name.
   </para>
   <para>
    The behavior of the backup feature is specified in the<guibutton>Loading and
    Saving</guibutton> pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default behavior is to back up the original contents
    to the buffer's file name suffixed with a tilde (<quote>~</quote>).
    For example, a file named <filename>paper.tex</filename> is backed up to
    <filename>paper.tex~</filename>.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
     The <guilabel>Max number of backups</guilabel> setting determines the
     number of backups to save. Setting this to zero disables the backup
     feature. Settings this to more than one adds numbered suffixes to file
     names. By default only one backup is saved.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     If the <guilabel>Backup directory</guilabel> setting is non-empty, backups
     are saved in that location. Otherwise, they are saved in the same directory
     as the original file. The latter is the default behavior.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     The <guilabel>Backup filename prefix</guilabel> setting is the prefix that
     is added to the backed-up file name. This is empty by default.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     The <guilabel>Backup filename suffix</guilabel> setting is the suffix that
     is added to the backed-up file name. This is <quote>~</quote> by default.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Backups can optionally be saved in a specified backup directory, instead of
     the directory of the original file. This can reduce clutter.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     The <guilabel>Backup on every save</guilabel> option is off by default,
     which results in a backup only being created the first time a buffer is
     saved in an editing session. If switched on, backups are
     created every time a buffer is saved.
    </para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="line-separators"><title>Line Separators</title>
  <para>
   Unix systems use newlines (<literal>\n</literal>) to mark line endings in
   text files. The MacOS uses carriage-returns (<literal>\r</literal>).
   Windows uses a carriage-return followed by a newline
   (<literal>\r\n</literal>). jEdit can read and write files in all three formats.
  </para>
  <para>
   The line separator used by the in-memory representation of file
   contents is always the newline character.
   When a file is being loaded, the line separator used in the file on disk
   is stored in a per-buffer property, and all line-endings are converted to
   newline characters for the in-memory representation.
   When the buffer is consequently saved, the value of the property replaces
   newline characters when the buffer is saved to disk.
   The line separator used by a buffer can be changed in
   the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Buffer
   Options</guimenuitem> dialog box. See <xref linkend="buffer-opts" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   By default, new files are saved with your operating system's native line
   separator. This can be changed in the
   <guibutton>Loading and Saving</guibutton> pane of the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box; see <xref linkend="global-opts" />. Note that changing this
   setting has no effect on existing files.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="encodings"><title>Character Encodings</title>
  <para>
   An encoding specifies a way of storing characters on disk.
   jEdit can use any encoding supported by the Java platform.
   The current buffer's encoding is shown in the status
   bar.
  </para>
  <para>
   The default encoding, used to load and save files for which no
   other encoding is specified, can be set in the <guibutton>Loading and
   Saving</guibutton> pane of the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box.
  </para>
  <para>
   Unless you change the default encoding, jEdit will use your operating
   system's native default; <literal>MacRoman</literal> on the MacOS,
   <literal>Cp1252</literal> on Windows, and <literal>8859_1</literal> on
   Unix.
  </para>
  <para>
   To open a file stored using an encoding other than the default, select the
   encoding from the
   <guimenu>Commands</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Encoding</guisubmenu> menu of
   the file system browser before opening the file.
  </para>
  <para>
   The encoding to use when saving a specific buffer
   can be set in the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Buffer
   Options</guimenuitem> dialog box.
  </para>
  <para>
   If a file is opened
   without an explicit encoding specified and it appears in the recent file list,
   jEdit will use the encoding last used
   when working with that file; otherwise the default encoding will be used.
  </para>
  <para>
   Unfortunately, there
   is no way to obtain a list of all supported encodings using the Java APIs,
   so jEdit only lists a few of
   the most common encodings; however, any other supported encoding name can be
   typed in.
  </para>
  <sect2><title>Commonly Used Encodings</title>
   <para>
    The most frequently-used character encoding is ASCII, or <quote>American 
    Standard Code for Information Interchange</quote>. ASCII encodes Latin
    letters used in English, in addition to numbers and a range of punctuation
    characters.
    The ASCII character set consists of 127 characters, and it is unsuitable
    for anything but English text (and other file types which only use English
    characters, like most program source). jEdit will load and save files as
    ASCII if the <literal>ASCII</literal> encoding is used.
   </para>
   <para>
    Because ASCII is unsuitable for international use, most operating
    systems use an 8-bit extension of ASCII, with the first 127 characters
    remaining the same, and the rest used to encode accents, umlauts, and
    various less frequently used typographical marks. The three
    major
    operating systems all extend ASCII in a different way. Files written by
    Macintosh programs can be read using the <literal>MacRoman</literal>
    encoding; Windows text files are usually stored as
    <literal>Cp1252</literal>. In the Unix world, the <literal>8859_1</literal>
    character encoding has found widespread usage.
   </para>
   <para>
    On Windows, various other encodings, which are known as <firstterm>code
    pages</firstterm> and are identified by number, are used to
    store non-English text. The corresponding Java encoding name is
    <literal>Cp</literal> followed by the code page number.
   </para>
   <para>
    Many common cross-platform international character sets are also supported;
    <literal>KOI8_R</literal> for Russian text, <literal>Big5</literal> and
    <literal>GBK</literal> for Chinese, and <literal>SJIS</literal> for
    Japanese.
   </para>
   <para>
    16-bit Unicode files are automatically detected as such when opened, regardless of
    the encoding specified by the user. The closely-related
    <literal>UTF8</literal> encoding, which uses variable-length characters, is
    also supported, however UTF8 files are <emphasis>not</emphasis> auto-detected.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="vfs-browser"><title>The File System Browser</title>
  <para>
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>File System
   Browser</guimenuitem> displays the file system browser.
   By default, the file system browser is shown in a floating window.
   It can be set to dock into the view in the <guibutton>Docking</guibutton>
   pane of the <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global
   Options</guimenuitem> dialog box; see <xref linkend="docking" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   The file system browser can be customized in the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box.
  </para>
  <sect2><title>Navigating the File System</title>
   <para>
    The directory to browse is specified in the <guibutton>Path</guibutton> text
    field. Clicking the mouse in the text field automatically selects its
    contents allowing a new path to be quickly typed in. If a relative path is
    entered, it will be resolved relative to the current path. This text field
    remembers previously entered strings; see <xref linkend="history" />.
    The same list of previously browsed directories is also listed in the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Recent Directories</guisubmenu>
    menu; selecting one opens it in the file system browser.
   </para>
   <para>
    To browse a listed directory, double-click it (or if you have a three-button
    mouse, you can click the middle mouse button as well). Alternatively, click
    the disclosure
    widget next to a directory to list its contents in place.
   </para>
   <para>
    To browse higher up in the directory hierarchy, double-click one of the parent
    directories in the parent directory list.
   </para>
   <para>
    Files and directories in the file list are shown in different colors
    depending on what glob patterns their names match. The patterns and colors
    can be customized in the
    <guibutton>File System Browser</guibutton>&gt;<guibutton>Colors</guibutton>
    pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box.
   </para>
   <para>
    To see a specific set of files only (for example,
    those whose names end with <filename>.java</filename>), enter a glob pattern
    in the <guibutton>Filter</guibutton> text field.
    This text fields remembers previously entered strings.
   </para>
   <para>
    See <xref linkend="globs" /> for information about glob patterns.
   </para>
   <para>
    Unopened files can be opened by double-clicking (or by
    clicking the middle mouse button). Open files have their names underlined,
    and can be selected by single-clicking.
    Holding down <keycap>Shift</keycap>
    while opening a file will open it in a new view.
   </para>
   <para>
    Clicking a file or directory with the right mouse button displays a popup
    menu containing various commands. <!-- Note that attempting to delete
    a directory containing files will give an error;
    only empty directories can be deleted. -->
   </para>
   <tip>
    <para>
     The file list sorting algorithm used in jEdit handles numbers in file names
     in an intelligent manner. For example, a file named
     <filename>section10.xml</filename> will be placed after a file named
     <filename>section5.xml</filename>. A conventional letter-by-letter
     sort would have placed these two files in the wrong order.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>The Tool Bar</title>
   <para>
    The file system browser has a tool bar containing a number of buttons.
    Each item in the <guibutton>Commands</guibutton>
    menu (described below) except
    <guimenuitem>Show Hidden Files</guimenuitem> and
    <guisubmenu>Encoding</guisubmenu> has a corresponding tool bar button.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>The Commands Menu</title>
   <para>
    Clicking the <guibutton>Commands</guibutton> button displays a menu
    containing the following items:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Parent Directory</guimenuitem> - moves up in
    the directory hierarchy.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Reload Directory</guimenuitem> - reloads the
    file list from disk.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Root Directory</guimenuitem> - on Unix,
    goes to the root directory (<filename>/</filename>). On Windows and MacOS X,
    lists all mounted drives and network shares.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Home Directory</guimenuitem> - displays your
    home directory.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Directory of Current Buffer</guimenuitem> - displays the
    directory containing the currently active buffer.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>New File</guimenuitem> - opens new, empty,
    buffer in the current directory. The file will
    not actually be created on disk until the buffer is saved.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>New Directory</guimenuitem> - creates a new
    directory after prompting for the desired name.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Search in Directory</guimenuitem> -
    displays the search and
    replace dialog box set to search all files in the current directory. If a
    file is selected when this command is invoked, its extension becomes the
    file name filter for the search;
    otherwise, the file name filter entered in the browser is used.
    See <xref linkend="search-replace" /> for details.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guimenuitem>Show Hidden Files</guimenuitem> - toggles if
    hidden files are to be shown in the file list.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><guisubmenu>Encoding</guisubmenu> - a menu for selecting
    the character encoding to use when opening files. See
    <xref linkend="encodings"/>.</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>The Plugins Menu</title>
   <para>
    Clicking the <guibutton>Plugins</guibutton> button displays a menu
    containing plugin commands. For information
    about plugins, see <xref linkend="using-plugins" />.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>The Favorites Menu</title>
   <para>
    Clicking the <guibutton>Favorites</guibutton> button displays a menu
    showing all directories in the favorites list. To add the selected directory
    to the favorites
    (or the current directory, if there is no selection), invoke
    <guimenuitem>Add to Favorites</guimenuitem> from this menu. To remove
    a directory from the favorites, invoke
    <guimenuitem>Edit Favorites</guimenuitem>, which will show the favorites
    list in the file system view; then select <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>
    from the appropriate directory's right-click menu.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>Keyboard Shortcuts</title>
   <para>
    The file system browser can be navigated from the keyboard:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><keycap>Enter</keycap> - opens the currently selected file or
    directory.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
    <keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo> - opens the currently selected file in a
    new view, or the currently selected directory in a new file system browser
    window.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><keycap>Left</keycap> - goes to the current directory's parent.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><keycap>Up</keycap> - selects previous file in list.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><keycap>Down</keycap> - selects next file in list.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><keycap>/</keycap> - displays the root directory.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><keycap>~</keycap> - displays your home directory.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><keycap>-</keycap> - displays the directory containing
    the current buffer.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Typing the first few characters of
    a file's name will select that file.
    </para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The file system tree must have keyboard focus for these
    shortcuts to work. They are not active in the <guibutton>Path</guibutton> or
    <guibutton>Filter</guibutton> text fields.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="reloading"><title>Reloading From Disk</title>
  <para>
   If an open buffer is modified on disk by another application, a warning
   dialog box is displayed, offering to either continue editing
   and lose changes made by the other application,
   or to reload the buffer from disk and lose any unsaved changes made in jEdit.
   This warning dialog box can be disabled in the <guibutton>General</guibutton>
   pane of the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box; see <xref linkend="global-opts" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Reload</guimenuitem> can be used to
   reload the current buffer from disk at any other
   time; a confirmation dialog box will be displayed first if the buffer
   has unsaved changes.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Reload All</guimenuitem>
   discards unsaved changes in all open buffers and reload them from disk,
   asking for confirmation first.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="threaded-io"><title>Multi-Threaded I/O</title>
  <para>
   To improve responsiveness and perceived performance,
   jEdit executes all buffer input/output operations asynchronously.
   While I/O is in progress, the status bar displays the number of
   remaining I/O operations.
   The <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guisubmenu>Troubleshooting</guisubmenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>I/O
   Progress
   Monitor</guimenuitem> command displays a window with more detailed status
   information and progress meters. This window is floating by default, but
   it can be set to dock into the view in the
   <guibutton>Docking</guibutton> pane of the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box; see <xref linkend="docking" />. I/O requests can also be aborted in
   this window, however note that aborting a buffer save can result in data loss.
  </para>
  <!-- <para>
   By default, four I/O threads are created, which means that up
   to four buffers can be loaded or saved simultaneously. The number of
   threads can be changed in the
   <guibutton>Loading and Saving</guibutton> pane of the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
   dialog box; see <xref linkend="global-opts" />. Setting the number to zero
   disables multi-threaded I/O completely; doing this is not recommended.
  </para> -->
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="printing"><title>Printing</title>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>P</keycap></keycombo>)
   prints the current buffer.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Page Setup</guimenuitem>
   displays a dialog box for changing your operating system's print settings,
   such as margins, page size, print quality, and so on.
  </para>
  <para>
   The print output
   can be customized in the <guibutton>Printing</guibutton> pane of the
   <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global
   Options</guimenuitem> dialog box. The following settings can be changed:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>The font to use when printing.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>If a header with the file name should be printed on each
   page.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>If a footer with the page number and current date should be
   printed on each page.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>If line numbers should be printed.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>If the output should be color or black and white.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>The tab size to use when printing - this will usually be
   less than the text area tab size, to conserve space in the printed output.
   </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="closing-exiting"><title>Closing Files and Exiting jEdit</title>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>W</keycap></keycombo>)
   closes the current buffer. If it has unsaved changes, jEdit
   will ask if they should be saved first.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Close All</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
   <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>W</keycap></keycombo>)
   closes all buffers. If any buffers have unsaved
   changes, they will be listed in a dialog box where they can be saved
   or discarded. In the dialog box, multiple buffers to operate on at
   once can be selected by clicking on them in the list while holding
   down <keycap>Control</keycap>. After all buffers have been closed, a new
   untitled buffer is opened.
  </para>
  <para>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Exit</guimenuitem>
   (shortcut: <keycombo><keycap>Control</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>)
   will completely exit jEdit, prompting if unsaved buffers should be saved
   first.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
