<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix id="history">
    <title>History Text Fields</title>
    <!-- jEdit buffer-local properties: -->
    <!-- :indentSize=1:noTabs=true: -->
    <!-- :xml.root=users-guide.xml: -->

    <para>The text fields in many jEdit components, such as the file system
    browser, incremental search bar, and action bar, all remember the last 20
    entered strings by default. The number of strings to remember can be changed
    in the <guibutton>Appearance</guibutton> pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box; see <xref linkend="appearance-pane" />.</para>

    <para>Pressing <keycap>UP</keycap> recalls previous strings. Pressing
    <keycap>DOWN</keycap> after recalling previous strings recalls later
    strings.</para>

    <para>Pressing <keycap>S+UP</keycap> or <keycap>S+DOWN</keycap> will search
    backwards or forwards, respectively, for strings beginning with the text
    already entered in the text field.</para>

    <para>Clicking the triangle to the right of the text field, or clicking with
    the right-mouse button anywhere else will display a pop-up menu of all
    previously entered strings; selecting one will input it into the text field.
    Selecting the first item, "previously entered strings:" pops up
    a dialog that lets you change previously entered strings.
    Holding down <keycap>Shift</keycap> while clicking will display a menu of
    all previously entered strings that begin with the text already
    entered.</para>

    <note>
        <title>Search and Replace fields</title>

        <para>In jEdit 4.3, the search/replace history fields are multi-line
        textareas, so they no longer use the same single-line history textfield
        described above. The multiline history textarea behaves a little
        differently: <keycap>UP</keycap> and <keycap>DOWN</keycap> arrows go up
        and down a line in the textarea, instead of through the previously
        entered strings. <keycap>PageUp</keycap> and <keycap>PageDown</keycap>
        are used instead to select history strings, and there is no arrow combo
        button, although right-click will still show you the history as a
        context menu.</para>
    </note>
</appendix>