<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="starting">
    <title>Starting jEdit</title>

    <!-- jEdit buffer-local properties: -->
    <!-- :tabSize=1:indentSize=1:noTabs=true: -->
    <!-- :xml.root=users-guide.xml: -->

    <para>Exactly how jEdit is started depends on the operating system. For
    example, on Unix you can run <quote>jedit</quote> at the command line, or
    select jEdit from a menu; on Windows, you can double-click on the jEdit icon
    or select it from the <guimenu>Start</guimenu> menu. </para>

    <para>If jEdit is started while another copy is already running, control is
    transferred to the running copy, and a second instance is not loaded. This
    saves time and memory if jEdit is started multiple times. Communication
    between instances of jEdit is implemented using TCP/IP sockets; the initial
    instance is known as the <firstterm>server</firstterm>, and subsequent
    invocations are <firstterm>clients</firstterm>.</para>

    <para>If you find yourself launching and exiting jEdit a lot, the startup
    time can get a bit bothersome. If the <userinput>-background</userinput>
    command line switch is specified, jEdit will continue running and waiting
    for client requests even after all editor windows are closed. When run in
    background mode, you can open and close jEdit any number of times, only
    having to wait for it to start the first time. The downside of this is
    increased memory usage.</para>

    <para>When running on MacOS X, the <userinput>-background</userinput>
    command-line switch is active by default, so that jEdit conforms to the
    platform convention that programs should stay open until the
    <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> command is explicitly invoked by the user,
    even if all windows are closed. To disable background mode on MacOS X, use
    the <userinput>-nobackground</userinput> switch.</para>

    <para>For more information about command line switches that control the
    server feature, see <xref linkend="cli-usage" />. </para>

    <para>jEdit remembers open buffers, views and split window configurations
    between editing sessions, so you can get back to work immediately after
    starting jEdit. This feature can be disabled in the
    <guibutton>General</guibutton> pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box see <xref linkend="general-pane" />.</para>

    <sidebar>
        <title>The edit server and security</title>

        <para>Since Java does not provide any interprocess communication
        facility other than TCP/IP, jEdit takes extra precautions to prevent
        remote attacks.</para>

        <para>Not only does the edit server pick a random TCP port number on
        startup, it also requires that clients provide an
        <firstterm>authorization key</firstterm>; a randomly-generated number
        only accessible to processes running on the local machine. So not only
        will <quote>bad guys</quote> have to guess a 64-bit integer, they will
        need to get it right on the first try; the edit server shuts itself off
        upon receiving an invalid packet.</para>

        <para>In environments that demand absolute security, the edit server can
        be disabled by specifying the <userinput>-noserver</userinput> command
        line switch.</para>
    </sidebar>

    <section id="cli-usage">
        <title>Command Line Usage</title>

        <para>On operating systems that support a command line, jEdit can be
        passed various arguments to control its behavior.</para>


        <para>When opening files from the command line, a line number or marker
        to position the caret on can be specified like so:</para>

        <screen><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>jedit MyApplet.java +line:10</userinput>
<prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>jedit thesis.tex +marker:c</userinput></screen>

        <para>Command-line switches begin with a "-". Some take a parameter. A
        file whose name begins with "-" can be opened like so:</para>

        <screen><prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>jedit -- -myfile</userinput></screen>

        <section>
            <title>Miscellaneous Options</title>

            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1.5in" />

                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Option</entry>

                            <entry>Effect</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-log=<replaceable>level</replaceable></userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Set the minimum log level to an integer
                            between 1 and 9. Default is 7. Has no effect when
                            connecting to another instance via the edit
                            server.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-usage</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Show a brief command line usage message
                            without starting jEdit. This message is also shown if
                            an invalid switch was specified.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-version</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Show the version number without starting
                            jEdit.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-nosplash</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Don't show the splash screen on startup.
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>--</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Specifies the end of command-line processing.
                            Further parameters are treated as file names, even if
                            they begin with a dash.</entry>
                        </row>

                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Configuration Options</title>

            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1.5in" />

                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Option</entry>

                            <entry>Effect</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-plugins</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Enable loading of plugins. Has no effect when
                            connecting to another instance via the edit server.
                            See <xref linkend="using-plugins" />.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-noplugins</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Disable loading of plugins. Has no effect when
                            connecting to another instance via the edit
                            server.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-restore</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Restore previously open files on startup. This
                            is the default. This feature can also be set
                            permanently in the <guibutton>General</guibutton>
                            pane of the
                            <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global
                            Options</guimenuitem> dialog box; see <xref
                            linkend="general-pane" />.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-norestore</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Do not restore previously open files on
                            startup.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-run=<replaceable>script</replaceable></userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Run the specified BeanShell script. There can
                            only be one of these parameters on the command line.
                            See <xref linkend="scripts-command-line" />.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-settings=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Store user-specific settings in the directory
                            named <replaceable>dir</replaceable>, instead of the
                            default
                            <filename><replaceable>user.home</replaceable>/.jedit</filename>.
                            The directory will be created automatically if it
                            does not exist. Has no effect when connecting to
                            another instance via the edit server. See <xref
                            linkend="settings-directory" />.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-nosettings</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Start jEdit without loading user-specific
                            settings.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-startupscripts</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Run startup scripts. This is the default. Has
                            no effect when connecting to another instance via the
                            edit server. See <xref
                            linkend="startup-scripts" />.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-nostartupscripts</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Disable startup scripts. Has no effect when
                            connecting to another instance via the edit
                            server.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Edit Server Options</title>

            <para>See <xref linkend="starting" /> for a brief description of the
            edit server.</para>

            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1.5in" />

                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Option</entry>

                            <entry>Effect</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-background</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Run jEdit in background mode. In background
                            mode, the edit server will continue listening for
                            client connections even after all views are closed.
                            Has no effect when connecting to another instance via
                            the edit server.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-nobackground</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Disable background mode. This is the default.
                            Has no effect when connecting to another instance via
                            the edit server.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-gui</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Open an initial view. This is the default. Has
                            no effect when connecting to another instance via the
                            edit server.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-nogui</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Do not open an initial view, and instead only
                            open one when the first client connects. Can only be
                            used in combination with the
                            <userinput>-background</userinput> switch. You can
                            use this switch to <quote>pre-load</quote> jEdit when
                            you log in to your computer, for example. Has no
                            effect when connecting to another instance via the
                            edit server.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-newplainview</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Opens the specified files in a new plain view.
                            For more information about views, see <xref
                            linkend="views" />.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-newview</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Opens the specified files in a new
                            view.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-reuseview</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Opens the specified files in an existing
                            view.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-quit</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Exits the currently running editor
                            instance.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-server</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Store the server port info in the file named
                            <filename>server</filename> inside the settings
                            directory.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-server=<replaceable>name</replaceable></userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Store the server port info in the file named
                            <replaceable>name</replaceable>. File names for this
                            parameter are relative to the settings
                            directory.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-noserver</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Do not attempt to connect to a running edit
                            server, and do not start one either.</entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry><userinput>-wait</userinput></entry>

                            <entry>Keeps the client open until the user closes
                            the specified buffer in the server instance. Does
                            nothing if passed to the initial jEdit instance. Use
                            this switch if jEdit is being invoked by another
                            program as an external editor; otherwise the client
                            will exit immediately and the invoking program will
                            assume you have finished editing the given
                            file.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
