<!-- jEdit buffer-local properties: -->
<!-- :tabSize=1:indentSize=1:noTabs=true:wrap=soft:maxLineLen=80: -->

<chapter id="using-plugins"><title>Installing and Using Plugins</title>
 <para>
  A <firstterm>plugin</firstterm> is an application which is loaded and runs
  as part of another, host application. Plugins respond to user commands
  and perform tasks that supplement the host application's features.
 </para>
 <para>
  This chapter covers installing, updating and removing plugins. Documentation
  for the plugins themselves can be found in
  <guimenu>Help</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>jEdit Help</guimenuitem>, and
  information about writing plugins can be found in <xref
  linkend="writing-plugins-part" />.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="plugin-manager"><title>The Plugin Manager</title>
  <para>
   <guimenu>Plugins</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Plugin Manager</guimenuitem>
   displays the plugin manager window. The plugin manager lists all installed
   plugins; clicking on a plugin in the list will display information about it.
  </para>
  <para>
   To remove plugins, select them (multiple plugins can be selected by
   holding down <keycap>Control</keycap>) and click <guibutton>Remove
   Plugins</guibutton>. This will display a confirmation dialog box first.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="installing-plugins"><title>Installing Plugins</title>
  <para>
   Plugins can be installed in two ways; manually, and from the plugin manager.
   In most cases, plugins should be installed from the plugin manager. It is
   easier and more convenient.
  </para>
  <para>
   To install plugins manually, go to <ulink
   url="http://plugins.jedit.org">http://plugins.jedit.org</ulink> in a web
   browser and follow the directions on that page.
  </para>
  <para>
   To install plugins from the plugin manager, make sure you are connected to
   the Internet and click the <guibutton>Install Plugins</guibutton> button in
   the plugin manager window. The plugin manager will then download information
   about available plugins from the jEdit web site, and present a list of
   plugins compatible with your jEdit release which may be installed.
  </para>
  <para>
   Click on a plugin in the list to see some information about it. To select
   plugins for installation, click the check box next to their names in the list.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guibutton>Total download size</guibutton> field shows the total size
   of all plugins chosen for installation, along with any plugins that will be
   automatically downloaded in order to fulfill dependencies. The
   <guibutton>Download size</guibutton> field in the plugin information area
   only shows the size of the currently selected plugin.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guibutton>Install source code</guibutton> check box controls if source
   code for the plugins should be downloaded and installed. Unless you are a
   developer, you probably don't need the source.
  </para>
  <para>
   The two radio buttons select the location
   where the plugins are to be installed.
   Plugins can be installed in either the <filename>jars</filename> subdirectory
   of the jEdit installation directory, or the <filename>jars</filename>
   subdirectory of the user-specific settings directory. For information about
   the settings directory, <xref linkend="settings-directory" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   Once you have specified plugins to install, click <guibutton>Install
   Plugins</guibutton> to begin the download process. Once all plugins have been
   downloaded and installed, a dialog box is shown advising that jEdit must be
   restarted before plugins can be used.
  </para>
  <sidebar><title>Proxy Servers and Firewalls</title>
   <para>
    If you are connected to the Internet through an HTTP proxy or SOCKS firewall,
    you will need to specify the relevant details in the
    <guibutton>Proxy Servers</guibutton> pane of the
    <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>&gt;<guimenuitem>Global Options</guimenuitem>
    dialog box.
   </para>
  </sidebar>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="updating-plugins"><title>Updating Plugins</title>
  <para>
   Clicking <guibutton>Update Plugins</guibutton> in the plugin manager will
   show a dialog box very similar to the one for installing plugins. It will
   list plugins for which updated versions are available. It will also offer to
   delete any obsolete plugins.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
