<!-- jEdit buffer-local properties:                     -->
<!-- :indentSize=1:noTabs=true:maxLineLen=72:tabSize=2: -->

<!-- jEdit FAQ									        -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2002 John Gellene                    -->

<!-- $Id$
-->



<sect1 id="other-customizing"><title>Other Ways to Customize jEdit</title>
<para>
  This section deals with other ways in which you can customize jEdit's appearance and
  behavior.
</para>

<qandaset>

<qandadiv id="customize-other"><title>Other Settings and Options</title>

<qandaentry>
	<question id="settings-change-font">
		<para>
			How can I change the font used for menu labels and other elements of jEdit's
			user interface?
		</para>
	</question>
	<answer>
		<para>
			Open the file [jedit install directory]/startup/changeUIFonts.bsh; near the end
			is the line:
<programlisting>
// changeUIFonts("SansSerif", Font.PLAIN, 12);
</programlisting>
			<quote>Uncomment</quote> this line by removing the <quote>//</quote> from the beginning, and
			change the font specification as desired. The new font will be used next time
			you start jEdit.
		</para>
	</answer>
</qandaentry>

</qandadiv>


</qandaset>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="macros"><title>Working with Macros</title>
<para>
  [Introduction, followed by question and answer set]
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="plugins"><title>Working with Plugins</title>
<para>
  This section deals with questions concerning the use of jEdit's
  plugins.  PLugins are applications that share jEdit's memory space
  and user interface and provide a wide variety of functions and
  services.
</para>

<qandaset>

<qandadiv id="plugin-general"><title>General plugin questions</title>

<qandaentry>
  <question id="plugins-latest-official">
    <para>
      Where can I get information on the latest available
      <quote>official</quote> plugins?
    </para>
  </question>
  <answer>
    <para>
      To get a listing of the latest plugins available for downloading from
      jEdit Plugin Central, use the <guimenuitem>Plugin Manager</guimenuitem>guimenuitem>
      feature on jEdit's <guimenu>Plugin</guimenu> menu. You can also get more
      detailed descriptions of the plugins from the <ulink
      ulink="http://plugins.jedit.org">Plugin Central</ulink> web site.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
  <question id="plugins-latest-beta">
    <para>
      Where can I get information on new plugins under development?
    </para>
  </question>
  <answer>
    <para>
      Many plugin developers make beta versions of their plugins available for
      downloading on the <ulink url="http://community.jedit.org">jEdit
      Community</ulink> web site.  Check the <quote>Plugin beta
      versions</quote> section of the web site's <quote>Downloads</quote>
      area.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
  <question id="plugins-developing">
    <para>
      How do I write a plugin?
    </para>
  </question>
  <answer>
    <para>
      Writing a plugin requires a working knowledge of Java and some
      familiarity with jEdit's Plugin API.  There is a tutorial on
      plugin development in the jEdit User's Guide.  The source
      code distribution for jEdit also includes the source for
      an example plugin, <application>Quick Notepad</application>, which
      is discussed in the tutorial.
    </para>
    <para>
      To learn more about plugin development, take a look at the source
      code for other plugins, particularly those whose features or user
      interface you might use as a model.  The <ulink
      url="mailto:devel@jedit.org">jedit-devel mailing list</ulink> and
      the message boards at <ulink url="http://community.jedit.org">jEdit
      Community</ulink> are also available for specific questions.
    </para>
  </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
	<question id="plugin-irc">
		<para>
			Is there an IRC (Internet Relay Chat) plugin for jEdit?
		</para>
	</question>
	<answer>
		<para>
			Yes. Open the Plugin Manager, then select <guimenuitem>Install
			plugins</guimenuitem>. You will find the
			IRC plugin which you can select for installation.
		</para>
	</answer>
</qandaentry>

</qandadiv>

</qandaset>

</sect1>

