<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- QuickNotepad 2.0 help documentation -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2001 John Gellene	 -->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="QuickNotepad">
    <articleinfo>
        <author>
            <firstname>John</firstname>

            <surname>Gellene</surname>

            <affiliation>
                <address><email>jgellene@nyc.rr.com</email></address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>

        <copyright>
            <year>2001</year>

            <holder>John Gellene</holder>
        </copyright>

        <legalnotice>
            <title>Legal Notice</title>

            <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
            document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
            Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free Software
            Foundation; with no <quote>Invariant Sections</quote>,
            <quote>Front-Cover Texts</quote> or <quote>Back-Cover Texts</quote>,
            each as defined in the license. A copy of the license is included in
            the file <filename>COPYING.DOC.txt</filename> included with the
            jEdit distribution.</para>
        </legalnotice>

        <title>QuickNotepad 4.2</title>
    </articleinfo>

    <simplesect>
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <indexterm>
            <primary>QuickNotepad</primary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>This plugin provides a dockable <quote>scratch pad</quote> for
        writing and displaying notes, to do lists or similar items as
        unformatted text. The text is automatically saved upon closing the
        plugin or exiting jEdit. It can also be saved manually. The user can
        change the file to be displayed during the current editing session. The
        path of the default notepad file can be changed as a user option.
        Finally, the text file can be copied to a new, untitled jEdit buffer so
        that it can be edited by the main program.</para>

        <para>The <citetitle>jEdit Plugin Guide</citetitle> details the
        development and design of QuickNotepad. It is a simple but functional
        dockable plugin that incorporates the basic elements of the jEdit plugin
        architecture.</para>

        <para>The file <filename>changes42.txt</filename> in the plugin's source
        code details the changes that were made to the plugin to conform to the
        new plugin API for jEdit version 4.2.</para>

        <para>The file <filename>changes40.txt</filename> in the plugin's source
        code details the changes that were made to the plugin to conform to the
        new plugin API for jEdit version 4.0.</para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
        <title>Operation</title>

        <para><indexterm>
                <primary>QuickNotepad</primary>

                <secondary>shortcut keys</secondary>
            </indexterm> When QuickNotepad is activated, it loads and displays
        the file stored in its properties as unformatted text. The text can be
        edited using the keyboard and mouse. The text area component recognizes
        the following basic editing shortcuts:</para>

        <!-- Limitations on xsltproc's capabilities require a blank column between -->

        <!-- the two columns of data to provide spacing for the table.       -->

        <informaltable frame="none">
            <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
                <colspec colnum="1" />

                <!-- blank column -->

                <colspec colnum="2" />

                <colspec colnum="3" />

                <!-- blank column -->

                <colspec colnum="4" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry>Cut</entry>

                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry><keycombo action="simul">
                                <keysym>Ctrl</keysym>

                                <keysym>x</keysym>
                            </keycombo></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry>Copy</entry>

                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry><keycombo action="simul">
                                <keysym>Ctrl</keysym>

                                <keysym>c</keysym>
                            </keycombo></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry>Paste</entry>

                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry><keycombo action="simul">
                                <keysym>Ctrl</keysym>

                                <keysym>v</keysym>
                            </keycombo></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry>Select All</entry>

                        <entry></entry>

                        <entry><keycombo action="simul">
                                <keysym>Ctrl</keysym>

                                <keysym>a</keysym>
                            </keycombo></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <para>QuickNotepad ignores function keys and other combination key
        presses.</para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
        <title>Toolbar buttons</title>

        <para>Three buttons above the text area provide file management
        operations:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Choose notepad file</guilabel> - this button
                opens a file selection dialog permitting the user to select a
                different file to view in the text area. If a new file is
                selected, the old file is auomatically saved. The selection is
                valid only for the current editing session; to change the
                default QuickNotepad file for future sessions, use the <link
                linkend="options">options dialog</link>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Save notepad file</guilabel> - this button
                causes QuickNotepad to write the contents of the text area to
                the designated notepad file. To save the text to another file
                name, use the <guilabel>Copy notepad to buffer</guilabel>
                operation.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Copy notepad to buffer</guilabel> - this button
                causes the contents of the text to be written to a newly
                created, untitled buffer in the main text editing area. This
                operation does not alter the QuickNotepad text area or write its
                text to storage. Further changes to either the QuickNotepad text
                area or the new buffer will not affect the other.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>These operations are listed in the menu which appears for
        QuickNotepad under the <guimenu>Plugins</guimenu> heading. They can also
        be made the subject of keyboard shortcuts in the <guilabel>Plugin
        Shortcuts</guilabel> pane of jEdit's options dialog.</para>

        <para>One other operation is available as a keyboard shortcut.
        <guilabel>Bring QuickNotepad to front</guilabel> activates the plugin
        and makes visible if it is currently hidden in a docking window.</para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id="options">
        <title>Options</title>

        <indexterm>
            <primary>QuickNotepad</primary>

            <secondary>options</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>There are three options which can be set using the pane for
        QuickNotepad in the <guilabel>Plugin Shortcuts</guilabel> section of the
        general options dialog:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>A checkbox governs whether the name of the notepad file
                will be displayed in the toolbar panel above the text area. Even
                if the file name display is enabled, if the plugin is displayed
                to the left or right of the main editing area, the notepad file
                name will likely be partially or completely hidden.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>A text field and adjacent button allow the user to choose
                the path of the default notepad file by typing its name or
                opening a file chooser dialog. This file will be loaded (and the
                old file saved) once the plugin's options settings are
                committed.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>A third button shows the name, size and style of the font
                used by the QuickNotepad text area. Pressing the button summons
                a font chooser dialog for making a new selection. The text area
                will be redrawn with the new font once the change is
                committed.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
        <title>Legal notices</title>

        <para>The QuickNotepad plugin is released under the GNU General Public
        License (either version 2 or any later version, at the user's option). A
        copy of the GPL is available in the <filename>COPYING.txt</filename>
        file in the jEdit distribution.</para>

        <para>The QuickNotepad plugin comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY OF ANY
        KIND; see section 11 and 12 of the GPL for details.</para>

        <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
        document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
        1.1 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
        no <quote>Invariant Sections</quote>, <quote>Front-Cover Texts</quote>
        or <quote>Back-Cover Texts</quote>, each as defined in the license. A
        copy of the license is included in the file
        <filename>COPYING.DOC.txt</filename> included with the jEdit
        distribution.</para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
        <title>Feedback</title>

        <para>Comments, bug reports and other feedback may be sent to the <ulink
        url="mailto:jgellene@nyc.rr.com">author</ulink> or the jEdit-users
        mailing list.</para>
    </simplesect>
</article>