<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="installation">
    <title>Installation Questions</title>

    <!-- jEdit buffer-local properties:                      -->

    <!-- :indentSize=4:noTabs=false:maxLineLen=72:tabSize=4: -->

    <!-- :xml.root=faq.xml:                                  -->

    <!-- jEdit FAQ                                           -->

    <!-- Copyright (C) 2003 John Gellene, Kris Kopicki       -->

    <para>This section deals with installing jEdit using the Java-based
    installation program, as well as installation issues that are specific to
    particular operating systems.</para>

    <qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
        <qandadiv id="install-general">
            <title>General installation questions</title>

            <qandaentry>
                <question id="easy-howto-install">
                    <para>What is the easiest way to install jEdit?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>First, make sure you have a working installation of
                    the Java platform. To run jEdit, you will a platform package
                    having a version number of at least 1.6. If you do not
                    have the Java platform, we recommend downloading the larger
                    <quote>Software Development Kit</quote> (SDK), instead of
                    the smaller <quote>Java Runtime Environment</quote> (JRE),
                    because you will need the tools supplied with the SDK if you
                    will be using Java for development. You will need to know
                    the path of the Java application launcher, which is called
                    <filename>java.exe</filename> on Windows systems and simply
                    <filename>java</filename> on others.</para>

                    <para>Next, decide whether you want the current "stable"
                    version or the latest development version. As a general
                    rule, the stable version is a good choice for first-time
                    users. Download the Java installer for the version
                    you have chosen from the jEdit web site; it consists of a
                    single file with a name in the style
                    <filename>jeditXXXinstall.jar</filename>. This file is a
                    compressed archive containing all of the files you need for
                    jEdit to run as well as an installer application written in
                    Java. You can put this file anywhere on your hard disk that
                    is convenient.</para>

                    <para>To run the installer, do whatever you normally do to
                    run a Java jar archive. If this is your first time, follow
                    these steps:</para>

                    <procedure>
                        <step>
                            <para>Open a terminal or command interpreter
                            window.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Change the current directory to the directory
                            in which you have stored the jEdit installer
                            file.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Run this command: <userinput>[full path to java
                            application launcher] -jar
                            jeditXXXinstall.jar</userinput></para>
                        </step>
                    </procedure>

                    <para>The installer will load and display a series of
                    dialogs for selecting a few simple options, including the
                    directory in which you wish jEdit installed. It will also
                    tell you how much disk space you need for the main program
                    and various installation options.</para>

                    <para>If this is your first download of jEdit, you should
                    definitely install the set of macros that come with the
                    application. Many of them are useful for all programmers,
                    and even the ones you don't use can serve as models when you
                    eventually begin writing your own macros.</para>

                    <para>The installation process is very short. If you are
                    installing the program on Windows and you select the
                    jEditLauncher option, you should be able to start jEdit by
                    clicking on any of the icons that the installation program
                    provides. On other systems, you can enter
                    <userinput>jedit</userinput> in a terminal window or create
                    your own desktop or menu shortcut.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question id="java-web-start">
                    <para>Why is there no Java Web Start version of
                    jEdit?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>In Java Web Start, dynamically-loaded classes (ie,
                    plugins) run in a sandbox unless they are explicitly signed.
                    Also, the protocol handler API prevents protocol handlers
                    from being added if they are not loaded via the system class
                    loader (i.e via the Java Web Start class loader). So the
                    lack of plugin support and jeditresource protocol makes it
                    useless.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question id="install-upgrade">
                    <para>How do I upgrade from one release of jEdit to
                    another?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>Simply delete the existing jEdit directory and run the
                    installer (if any) to install the new version. Settings are
                    kept in <filename>~/.jedit</filename>, and will not be
                    affected.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
        </qandadiv>

        <qandadiv id="install-mac">
            <title>Installing jEdit on MacOS</title>

            <qandaentry>
                <question id="install.mac9-basic">
                    <para>How do I install jEdit on MacOS 8 or MacOS 9? s</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>The latest version of jEdit requires
                    MacOS X (preferably 10.5 or later), because the Java
                    platforms of earlier MacOS versions are outdated.</para>

                    <para>Once you have completed installing jEdit locate the
                    jedit.jar file and do the following:</para>

                    <procedure>
                        <step>
                            <para>Drag the <filename>jedit.jar</filename> to
                            JBinary and JBinary will launch.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>In the Command window in the Class path box
                            replace <userinput>jedit</userinput> with
                            <userinput>org.gjt.sp.jedit.jEdit</userinput>.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Then click the Save settings button. It will
                            ask for an application name and will create a
                            double-clickable icon on your desktop.</para>
                        </step>

                        <step>
                            <para>Double-click on your icon to launch
                            jEdit.</para>
                        </step>
                    </procedure>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>How do I uninstall jEdit for Mac OS?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>There are no system files, so simply drop the jEdit
                    folder in the trash. If you want to remove the settings
                    directory used by jEdit you will find it at
                    <filename>~/.jedit</filename>. It is hidden, so you will
                    need to remove it from the command line, or use one of the
                    various uilities available that will let you see it.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
        </qandadiv>

        <qandadiv id="install-windows">
            <title>Installing jEdit on Windows</title>

            <qandaentry>
                <question id="install-windows-basic">
                    <para>Is there anything different about installing jEdit on
                    Windows?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>For the Microsoft Windows family of operating systems,
                    jEdit provides an additional package of features called
                    jEditLauncher. These features include: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Built-in shortcut icons for launching
                                jEdit;</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Support for opening files in jEdit using custom
                                entries in the context (right-click) menu of the
                                Windows shell;</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Support for running BeanShell scripts in jEdit
                                from outside the application;</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Support for launching jEdit and loading files
                                using scripting languages such as VBScript, Perl and
                                Python;</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Automatic uninstallation of jEdit using the
                                <quote>Add/Remove Programs</quote> applet in Control
                                Panel.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist> The package is a recommended option that
                    is selected by default when you install jEdit. The Java
                    installer application launches a separate Windows installer
                    module for the native Windows executables that comprise the
                    jEditLauncher package. If the installation involves an
                    upgrade, you may be asked to reboot your computer to
                    complete the process.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question id="install-windows-components">
                    <para>Do I need any special Windows components to run
                    jEditLauncher?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>Regardless of the version of Windows that you use, if
                    you have kept it reasonably up-to-date with service packs or
                    component upgrades from Microsoft, you should have no
                    trouble running jEditLauncher. Users of Windows 98, Windows
                    ME, Windows NT (version 4.0), Windows 2000 and Windows XP
                    have not reported problems involving missing
                    components.</para>

                    <para>Some users of older versions of Windows 95 may need to
                    upgrade their version of the Windows Sockets package. Others
                    may be missing Microsoft's package for supporting DCOM
                    (Distributed Component Object Model) components on Windows
                    95. Both the <ulink
                    url="http://www.microsoft.com/windows95/downloads/contents/wuadmintools/s_wunetworkingtools/w95sockets2/">
                    Windows Sockets upgrade</ulink> and the <ulink
                    url="http://www.microsoft.com/com/dcom/dcom95/dcom1_3.asp">
                    DCOM package</ulink> are available for download from
                    Microsoft.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question id="install-windows-vm">
                    <para>Can I run jEdit on Microsoft's virtual machine?</para>
                </question>

                <answer>
                    <para>The latest version of jEdit requires at
                    least version 1.6 of the Java 2 platform, and therefore may
                    not be compatible with 3rd party virtual machines.</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
        </qandadiv>
    </qandaset>
</sect1>